<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the cross in baptism considered wherein is shewed that there is nothing in it as it is used in the Church of England that can be any just reason of separation from it.</title>
            <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57057</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24493</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08206479</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08206479</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41093</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57057)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41093)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1238:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the cross in baptism considered wherein is shewed that there is nothing in it as it is used in the Church of England that can be any just reason of separation from it.</title>
                  <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Fincham Gardiner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Nathanael Resbury.  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>This work also appears as the sixth item in v. 2 of: A collection of cases and other discources / by some divines of the city of London (Wing C5114).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cross, Sign of the --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41093:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF THE <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm</hi> CONSIDERED. Wherein is Shewed, That there is nothing in it, as it is uſed in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that can be any juſt Reaſon of Separation from it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Galat. VI. 14.</hi>
               </bibl> God forbid that I ſhould glory, ſave in the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Fincham Gardiner,</hi> at the <hi>White-Horſe</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:41093:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41093:2"/>
            <head>THE CASE OF THE CROSS IN Baptiſm, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Matters in Diſpute betwixt Us and our Diſſenting Brethren, may generally ſeem to the unconcern'd ſtander by, of ſo ſlight and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Moment, that he muſt needs wonder how in the World the Controverſie ſhould come to have ariſen to that Deplorable height, which in this laſt Age it hath done. And although the <hi>Caſe</hi> which will fall under our preſent Debate, ſeems to have admitted of the moſt ſpecious ſcruples and given the beſt ſcope of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, of any other thing that hath fallen under que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion amongſt us ſince the Reformation; yet even here alſo, the <hi>Immeaſurable Byaſs</hi> of Prejudice,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and Fervency of Oppoſition, hath too apparently manag'd the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So that the Pleas againſt it have not ſeem'd ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41093:3"/>
               <hi>weighty</hi> as they have been <hi>numerous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. 5. c. 20. <hi>Infirmiora Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumenta Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greganda ſunt, imbecilla enim natio â, mutuo auxilio ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentur.</hi>
               </note> as if the Objectors had an Eye to that direction in <hi>Quintilian,</hi> they would be ſure <hi>to amaſs all the weaker Arguments, which though weak in themſelves, yet by ſtanding together may lend a Mutual aſſiſtance to one another;</hi> like Articles of Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, none of which ſingly would perhaps affect the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd Perſon, but all together may amount to accumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Treaſon.</p>
            <p>My buſineſs therefore in handling this <hi>Caſe,</hi> ſhall not be to follow every nice Scruple, or trivial Objection (as where the <hi>Croſs</hi> in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> hath been charg'd with the breach of every particular Precept in the Decalogue) not to concern my ſelf in any thing, which either by long Induction of conſequences hath been far fetcht, or with great difficulty drawn in, to make a ſhow of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but, as briefly and plainly as may be to ſum up all that hath ever ſeem'd of any Moment in this matter, and that under this twofold Head.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the Sign of the <hi>Croſs</hi> hath been ſo notoriouſly abus'd to the worſt purpoſes of Superſtition and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> that the retaining of it ſtill amongſt us, makes us partakers of the Superſtitions and Idolatry of <hi>that Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. That it ſeem's the introducing of a <hi>New Sacrament,</hi> which having not the warranty of our Lord and Maſter <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> muſt needs be a very Offenſive invaſion of <hi>his</hi> Rights, whoſe Royal Prerogative alone it is to inſtitute what <hi>Sacraments</hi> he pleaſeth in <hi>his</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>Under theſe two Heads I think may be fairly compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended all thoſe Objections <hi>our Brethren</hi> have offer'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Sign of the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm,</hi> at leaſt all thoſe that are any thing Material. Inſomuch that if the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of theſe could be remov'd, we might fairly hope, none of the Sober and Conſcientious Diſſenters, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41093:3"/>would think themſelves oblig'd to ſubmit to the uſe of it, rather than maintain the Separation upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>And this ſhall be endeavour'd with all the Candor and Clearneſs that becomes the deſign of this, and the reſt of thoſe Diſcourſes that have been Publiſht of this kind, <hi>viz.</hi> to Convince and not Reproach or Provoke any: to Effect (if poſſible) the happy agreement, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently enlarge and ſtrengthen the intereſts of good Men. And for this purpoſe I have thought fit not to quote the writings of particular Perſons, but rather to repreſent the Objection, as what is in general avow'd and agreed upon by the whole Party.</p>
            <p>And although it is not likely that any thing ſhould be <hi>here</hi> offer'd, that hath not been already with great Learning and Integrity made uſe of, by the many aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of <hi>our Church;</hi> yet perhaps, the bringing this under one view, without the <hi>Warmth</hi> or <hi>Salt</hi> of an Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary may not prove altogether Vain and Ineffectual.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I begin therefore, with the firſt Objection, <hi>viz. That the Sign of the Croſs hath been ſo notoriouſly abus'd to the worſt purpoſes of Superſtition and Idolatry in the</hi> Church of Rome, <hi>that the retaining of it ſtill amongſt us, makes us Partakers of the Superſtitions and Idolatry of that</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>I muſt readily acknowledg that the Material Figure of the <hi>Croſs</hi> hath been indeed abus'd to very <hi>Idolatrous</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and even the aereal Sign of it to Purpoſes ſuperſtitious and ridiculous enough, and if what we do in uſing this Sign in Baptiſm, were real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chargeable with <hi>Popery,</hi> it would be a ſufficient reaſon to deteſt and Reject it. The Objection therefore at the firſt view looks plauſibly enough, when it thus chargeth this Ceremony of the <hi>Croſs;</hi> Paganiſm it ſelf being hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41093:4"/>more Odious, nor in Truth (for ſome very good Reaſons amongſt wiſe Men,) more Ridiculous and Into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable. There is ſcarce any part of <hi>Popery,</hi> properly ſo called, but is ſo plain a d'pravation of Chriſtianity it ſelf, ſuch a contradiction to the Rules, ſuch a defeat to the great purpoſes and ends of our <hi>Holy Religion,</hi> that it deſerves well enough the good Mans Juſteſt abhorrency, which he may reaſonably expreſs, when he finds himſelf in any real danger of the Snare. But then, we muſt conſider, how eaſie and natural a thing it is for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (that otherwiſe mean honeſtly enough) to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour a Juſt and Reaſonable Offence againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> into groundleſs Suſpicions upon things which have no ſuch Tendency at all in them: And upon theſe firſt Suſpicions not only to ſtartle, and grow alittle ſhy and nice, but to determine themſelves in reſolv'd &amp; unmoveable Prejudices, that have had Effects ill enough. For upon this, deſigning Men have made their advantage upon every trifling occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, giving out the word, and laying the charge of <hi>Popery,</hi> upon what it hath been their humour or intereſt to deſire a change in. And this probably we ſhall find to have happen'd in this <hi>Caſe</hi> in hand. The accuſation hath been drawn againſt it that it is very <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and the Prejudices which this Accuſation hath begot in ſome honeſt Minds, are ſo ſtrong that they ſeem invincible. How unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably therefore this charge is laid againſt our uſe of the <hi>Sign of the Croſs</hi> in Baptiſm may appear when we have conſidered theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the uſe of this Sign was much more ancient, than the firſt Corruption and Depravation of the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. That the uſe of it, as it is ordain'd and appointed in our <hi>Church,</hi> hath not the leaſt affinity with the uſe of it, as it is in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Rituals.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41093:4"/>
            <p n="3">III. Laſt. Although it cannot be deny'd but the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> hath greatly abus'd this Ceremony to very ill purpoſes of Superſtition, yet doth not this make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to continue the Reform'd uſe of it ſtill amongſt us that have profeſſedly ſeparated from the Corruptions of <hi>that Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Conſider we that the uſe of this Sign of the <hi>Croſs</hi> was much more ancient than the firſt Corruption and Depravation of the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> When I ſpeak of the <hi>firſt Corruption and Depravation</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I would be underſtood as to thoſe things that have put <hi>that Church</hi> under the Imputation of what we now call <hi>Popery.</hi> For that there were ſome deprav'd Cuſtoms crept into the Church in general (and ſo that of <hi>Rome</hi> perhaps as well as any other) in very early days, is Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from what St. <hi>Paul</hi> Rebukes in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and from what our Saviour himſelf in his <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> to St. <hi>John,</hi> Condemns in the Seven Churches of <hi>Aſia.</hi> So that, when I ſay the uſe of the <hi>Croſs</hi> was more ancient than the firſt Corruption and Depravation of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> I mean, more ancient than any of thoſe Corruptions in her by the reaſon of which, we have juſtly eſteem'd her an <hi>Apoſtatiz'd Church,</hi> more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient than either the Introduction of Images, their Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of Sacraments, their pretentions to Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy and Infallibility, or any of thoſe Superſtitious Rites in Worſhip, by which we diſtinguiſh <hi>that Church</hi> as <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and brand it as falſe and <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to this therefore,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>By which Phraſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in Truth meant, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret workings of the</hi> Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks <hi>of</hi> that <hi>Age.</hi>
               </note> I know none of our Diſſenting Brethren, however for a ſhift in Argument they may talk of the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> beginning to work betimes, and in the firſt Ages of the Church *, that yet do profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly charge any <hi>Signal</hi> Apoſtaſy upon the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> at leaſt for the firſt four hundred Years after Chriſt: not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41093:5"/>to the Age wherein St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> Flouriſht; but that it was a Church that might be Communicated with at that time, notwithſtanding <hi>that</hi> Father complain'd of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfaetation of Ceremonies even then, which (at leaſt for the Number of them) began to be very burdenſom. And yet, for an Hundred or two of Years before this, we find in the Writings of <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſuch mention of the uſe of <hi>this</hi> Sign, that makes it very plain, it had been a Cuſtomary thing long before his time alſo, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, even amongſt thoſe of the Apoſtolical Age it ſelf. There are thoſe indeed that would make that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the firſt that brought in the uſe of this Ceremony into the Church, having receiv'd it from the <hi>Montaniſts</hi> of whom he ſeems to have been particularly fond. But the frequent and familiar mention he makes of the Sign of the Croſs in many of his Books renders this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture very improbable. <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us it was grown ſo much in uſe in his time, that <hi>upon every motion of theirs,</hi> at their <hi>going out and coming in, when they put on their Garments or Shooes, at the Bath, or at Meals when they lighted up their Candles,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Frontem crueis ſignaculo tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> Pertul. <hi>de Coron. mil.</hi>
                  </note> or went to Bed, whatever al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt they did in any part of their Converſation, ſtill they would even wear out their Forheads with the Sign of the Croſs;</hi> which though he confeſſeth there was no expreſs Law of Chriſt that had enjoyn'd it, yet <hi>Tradition had Introduc'd, Cuſtom had Confirm'd, and the Believers Faith had obſerv'd and maintain'd it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This doth not look as if it had been a thing newly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by <hi>Montanus,</hi> and brought into the Church by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> as being himſelf too great a Favourer of that Sect. Although, were it thus indeed, yet this ſheweth that the Practice of it was receiv'd among the Faithful, ſome Ages before the Depravation and Apoſtacy of the <hi>Romiſh Church.</hi> But he is not our ſingle Author in this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41093:5"/>matter: for,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homil.</hi> 2. <hi>in Pſalm.</hi> 38.</note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> who Flouriſht not much above CC Years after Chriſt, and not XL Years after <hi>Tertullian,</hi> makes mention of thoſe who upon their Admiſſion into the Church by Baptiſm, <hi>were Sign'd with this Sign.</hi> And St. <hi>Baſil</hi> not much above one Hundred Years after him, gives this uſage the Venerable Title of <hi>an Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitution,</hi> or <hi>fixt Law of the Church, that had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd from the Apoſtles Days,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil. de Spir. Sanct. cap.</hi> 27.</note> that thoſe who believed in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould be Signed with the Sign of the Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of all the Fathers, St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who was before St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and very near if not contemporary with <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> himſelf, not only ſpeaks moſt Familiarly of the uſe of this Sign, but hath ſome Expreſſions in this matter, that would ſeem very harſh and unwarrantable now; and yet, the Authority of that Father, hath ſav'd him hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto from being brought under queſtion about it. He tells us in one place, that in <hi>fronte cruce ſignantur, qui Dominum promerentur,</hi> i.e. <hi>they are Sign'd in the Forehead with the Croſs who are thought worthy of the Lord,</hi> and in another place, <hi>Omnia ſacramenta peragit, it Compleats e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sacrament,</hi> and <hi>per crucem baptiſma ſanctificatur, Baptiſm is Sanctified by the Croſs.</hi> I will not ſtand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for the Juſtifiableneſs of theſe paſſages, were they to be allow'd no kind of Latitude: but, as to the purpoſe for which they are cited they ſeem pertinent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: that is, to Argue the antiquity of this uſage (and that in the Sacrament of Baptiſm too) the Phraſe ſo frequently occurring in the writings of thoſe ancient Fathers, that <hi>fronte ſignati, being ſign'd in the Forehead,</hi> ſeems a known and uſual <hi>Periphraſis</hi> for being enter'd into the Faith of Chriſt and the Body of his Church by Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>After all which, what need I Inſtance in St. <hi>Cyril,</hi> St.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41093:6"/>
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> or St. <hi>Auſtin?</hi> Who ſprinkle their writings with the Common mention of this Ceremony, and oftentimes frame Arguments of the Obligation upon Chriſtians to live as becomes them, from this very badg they wear upon their Foreheads. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> wittily enough glorying in the <hi>Confidence</hi> of a Chriſtian as to a <hi>Crucifi'd Saviour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec nos pudet Crucifixi, ſed ubi pudoris ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt, crucis ejus ſignum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus. Auguſt. in Galat.</hi> 6.14.</note> that he willingly imprints the Sign of it upon that part of himſelf <hi>which is the proper ſeat of Bluſhing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only add this remark further, that after the time wherein this Cuſtom had been ſo Univerſally receiv'd into the Chriſtian Church, and ſome of the Fathers had ſo liberally expreſt themſelves in it, we may obſerve that the firſt Chriſtian Emperour, <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> had his Directions probably from heaven it ſelf to make this Sign, the great Banner in his Wars, with this Additional encouragement,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that <hi>by this he ſhould overcome.</hi> That this <hi>Dream</hi> or <hi>Viſion</hi> (call it which we will, for Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries mention it differently) was from Heaven, and a thing of great reality, is Evident, from the ſucceſs of that Princes Arms under it.</p>
            <p>The Authors of the <hi>Centuries</hi> allow a conſiderable Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification in that Sign as given him from Heaven, as the future Standard he ſhould fight under, <hi>viz, that God had admoniſht him by that Sign of the Croſs, and the Motto ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cent.</hi> 4. <hi>oap.</hi> 13.</note> by this thou ſhalt overcome, <hi>concerning the Knowledg and Worſhip of the true God, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in Memorial of which he took care to have it Painted on his Banner, that it might be as the Symbol of the Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we would not ſuppoſe that our Bleſſed Lord would by ſo immediate a Revelation from Heaven, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſuch a Rite as this, already receiv'd and made uſe of in the Church, giving it to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> both as a Symbol of his Profeſſion, and Pledg of his future Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, if he had reſented it before as Superſtitious or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41093:6"/>any way unwarrantable. This kind of Standard the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours ſucceſſively had born before them in their Warrs: nay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodoret. Hiſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> it is recorded that <hi>Julian</hi> himſelf (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably from what he had made ſome former Obſervations of,) could not forbear defending himſelf with this Sign, upon a mighty fright he was ſeiz'd with, while in the uſe of Magick Arts he went to have conſulted with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orat. Cont.</hi> Julian.</note> This <hi>Nazianzen</hi> calls his <hi>craving aid and refuge of him whom he had Perſecuted.</hi> Which, (by the way) might give us the modeſtly and caution of ſhowing our ſelves too petulant againſt what it hath pleas'd our Lord Jeſus in a Revelation from Heaven to give the Figure of, and the Holy Spirit alſo to ſignalize ſometimes by very renown'd miracles, which thoſe that conſult Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hiſtories of beſt Authority cannot but be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of.</p>
            <p>So that, we find the uſe of it very ancient, and the Effects of it very Memorable,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exercit. in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronium.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caſaubon</hi> himſelf (no ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fond Man of Rituals) calls it <hi>Primitivae Eccleſiae Symbolum ejus fiduciae quam in Chriſto &amp; cruce ipſius, &amp; paſſione ponebant: a Symbol the Primitive Church uſed to denote that Confidence they had in Chriſt, his Croſs, and Paſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs it would be a fond thing to endeavour, with ſome of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> to trace up the Antiquity of the Croſs, to the firſt Creation of Man, and ſo all along downward to the Actual Death of our Bleſſed Lord. <hi>They</hi> can ſpy out the Croſs, in the Figure of a Man's Face, by the placing of the <hi>Noſe betwixt the two Eyes,</hi> and much more in the <hi>Poſition of the whole Body of the Man with his Arms extended.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the notes of Laur. le bar upon Tertul. adverſ. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 178, 179.</note> They can diſcern it <hi>in the Sword in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe,</hi> and in <hi>the Croſs ſtick that Noah's Dove brought back into the Ark,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And indeed ſome of the Fathers bend their Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſomthing that way, and would fancy the Figure of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41093:7"/>the Croſs in <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſtretching out his Arms whiles the Iſraelites were fighting with <hi>Amalek,</hi> in the <hi>Paſchal Lamb when the Spit went through it,</hi> &amp;c. which, however they were conceipts too much ſuiting that way of allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing that ſome of them were fond of, yet doth it at leaſt confirm what I am now upon, I mean the ancient Reception of this Sign into the Primitive Church. Nay, I may further add, that in ſome of the paſſages they have of this kind, the hint they take may not deſerve perhaps to be abſolutely exploded, as if there were no weight or moment at all in it. I will crave leave to inſtance par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in one thing which ſome of the Fathers do a little inſiſt upon, and that is, that <hi>Mark</hi> in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.4. that was <hi>to be ſet upon the Foreheads of the Men that ſigh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Mark</hi> in ſeveral of the ancient Verſions is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be the <hi>Hebrew Tau,</hi> which St. <hi>Hierom</hi> tells us was, in the Samaritan Character, like our T, and ſo made the figure of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> from whence he Collects that this was <hi>ſignum crucis quae in Chriſtianorum frontibus pingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, a token of that Croſs that is imprinted upon the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of the Chriſtian.</hi> If St. <hi>Hierom</hi> be not miſtaken in the Samaritan Character, his conjecture in the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, is not very unjuſtifiable; becauſe, as <hi>all the promiſes are in Chriſt Jeſus,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</note> yea, and in him Amen:</hi> So, all the Propheſies of old, where they concern'd any ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal advantages or deliverances to the Jewiſh Church had the aſſurance of them frequently confirm'd by ſome hint or Remembrance of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that was afterward to be reveal'd. Thus in that Confirmation that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was to give to <hi>Ahaz</hi> of his preſent deliverance from the Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 7.4.</note> he gives him this Sign, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a Virgin ſhall conceive and bear a Son.</hi> How could that great Event that was not to come to paſs of ſo many Ages after <hi>Ahaz</hi> his Death, affect him, who ſtood in need
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41093:7"/>of ſo immediate Deliverance, but that it was brought in as an inſtance, (not only that as God could bring about ſuch a wonder, as the Birth of a Child from a Virgin, could as eaſily relieve <hi>Judah</hi> in its preſent ſtreights: but further,) he that had ſo gracious a deſign toward them, as to ſend the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> amongſt them, would in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he had to that, ſhow now his particular regards for the Church at this time. In Analogy to this, might this paſſage in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> look toward that mark which Chriſtians in after Ages ſhould wear upon their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, as a preſent Symbol of the eſcape of thoſe that ſhould be found <hi>ſighing for the Abominations that were then done in Iſrael.</hi> And to this probably, may that <hi>Seal of the living God</hi> have ſome Reference, which was <hi>to be ſet upon the Foreheads of the Servants of God.</hi> Revel. 7.2, 3. For, as they are there reckon'd up by the number of <hi>twelve times twelve,</hi> to ſignifie that they are the true and genuine off-ſpring of the twelve Apoſtles; ſo,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Med. in loc.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Seal of the Living God upon their Foreheads,</hi> may point at the Figure of the Croſs, to betoken them (though under the Prophetick Denomination of the <hi>Jewiſh Tribes</hi>) to be of the <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi> This I would not be ſuppos'd to lay any great ſtreſs of Argument upon, only offer the Conjecture to the Candor of the Reader.</p>
            <p>And thus, having ſhewen the Antiquity of <hi>this Sign,</hi> as it was receiv'd into the Church long before the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of <hi>Popery</hi> appear'd in the World; I know but of one thing can be urg'd to take off the ſtrength of what hath been hitherto ſaid; and that is, that the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians might probably take up this Cuſtom of thus ſigning themſelves, becauſe they liv'd wholly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Enemies of the Croſs of Chriſt, the <hi>Jews making the Croſs a Stumbling-block, and the Greeks Fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs.</hi> So that, their deſign of doing it, was only to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41093:8"/>bear their Teſtimony to the Faces of both, that is, tho the Croſs was ſcandal to the one, and ſcorn and laughter to the other, yet they would not be aſhamed of this Croſs but made it the Badg of their Profeſſion. Whereas we live in an Age and Nation, where (thanks be to God) there ſeems no ſuch occaſion, becauſe Chriſtianity is the Religion we openly and univerſally profeſs.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that this Objection being thus made, doth at leaſt ſuppoſe the uſage of the Croſs not to be a thing that is in it ſelf evil, becauſe if ſo, no good end or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in uſing it could hallow the Action; ſo that the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony is not Evil in its ſelf, but that upon ſome weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaſons, it might be brought into the Church, if ſo, then we might reaſonably think, that the injunction of Authority in this Caſe, might Juſtifie the Practice of it. But much more, if the reaſon now alledg'd might be a juſt occaſion for the Church in its firſt Ages to take the uſage up, God knows the occaſion may be as urgent ſtill upon an Equally ſad account: and that is, the Prophane and Atheiſtical Contempt that is thrown, not ſo much upon the <hi>Sign</hi> as the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Croſs, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Wits of our Age. He hath a very ſlender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment for the intereſts of Religion, that is not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly toucht with thoſe Blaſphemous Railleries he may every where meet with, upon the whole Scheme of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, eſpecially that which we make the great Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our hopes and truſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the Merits of our Saviours Croſs and Paſſion. That the uſe of this Sign, if ever it was reaſonable upon ſuch a ſcore as this, it is ſo now. And St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> Caution is ſtrong and pertinent enough at this time of the day againſt all the Wit and Pride of the daring and haughty Atheiſt, <hi>Muniatur frons,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 56. <hi>ad Thiberitanos.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Arm your Foreheads that the Seal of God may be kept ſafe.</hi> q. d. <hi>Remember the Badg you took upon you in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41093:8"/>and ſo long as you have that upon your Foreheads, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be aſham'd or laught out of Countenance, as to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of your Saviours Love, and the Foundation of your hopes lay'd in his Death and Paſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, ſince it is ſo evident how Ancient a practice this hath been in the Chriſtian Church: I would not have this part of the Argument pretended further than it was firſt deſign'd, which was only to ſhow that this Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony hath nothing owing in it to that which we call <hi>Popery,</hi> becauſe it was eſtabliſht in the Church ſo long before that <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> had its being. And tho through the Antiquity of it (if warrantable at the firſt) it becomes ſo much the more Venerable, and might juſtly lay ſome reſtraints upon the modeſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in his Cenſures againſt it; yet doth not this put it beyond the degree of an <hi>indifferent Ceremony,</hi> without which, the Sacrament of Baptiſm is declar'd by our <hi>Church</hi> as complete and perfected. Did the Antiquity of its practice make it neceſſary, it might prove as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry almoſt in every Action of Life, as well as Baptiſm, becauſe (as I have noted before) <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us, it was once ſo uſed. No, it only gives us the warrant of doing it, becauſe practis'd in the moſt incorrupt Ages of Chriſtianity; and the neceſſity of keeping it ſtill in uſe, lyes not ſo much in that it was the Cuſtom of ſome Church, or Conſtitution of ſome Council in former days, as that it is the Cuſtom of our Church now, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of our Governours. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is further conſiderable, that the uſe of the Croſs as it is ordain'd and appointed in our <hi>Church,</hi> hath not the leaſt affinity with the uſe of it, as it is in the <hi>Romiſh Rituals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We do by no means allow any viſible Images of a Crucifi'd <hi>Jeſus,</hi> ſo as to have the leaſt concern in any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41093:9"/>part of our Worſhip. There is no mention of them in our Rubrick; there is hardly in any writings of the Doctors of our Church one paſſage to be found of that latitude,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſtian di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect. Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Caſes qu.</hi> 113. <hi>p.</hi> 875. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 876.</note> that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> amongſt his calmeſt thoughts hath not adventur'd to ſay, that is, that a <hi>Crucifix well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth the Imagination and Mind of a Believer;</hi> nay further, that it <hi>is not unlawful to make an Image</hi> (and gives the inſtance particularly of a <hi>Crucifix</hi>) <hi>to be the objectum vel medium excitans ad cultum Dei, an Object or medium of our conſideration, exciting our minds to Worſhip God.</hi> The ſenſe of our Church is truly expreſt in this matter by Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> who tells us that <hi>between the Croſs which Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition honoureth as Chriſt, and that Ceremony of the Croſs which ſerveth only for a ſign of Remembrance, there is as plain and great a difference, as between thoſe brazen Images which</hi> Solomon <hi>made to bear up the Ciſtern of the Temple,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ. Pol. l.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 348.</note> and that which the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>in the Wilderneſs did adore.</hi> Or <hi>between thoſe Altars which</hi> Joſias <hi>deſtroy'd, becauſe they were Inſtruments of meer Idolatry, and that which the tribe of</hi> Reuben <hi>with others erected near the River</hi> Jordan <hi>to far other purpoſes.</hi> Ours is no other than a meer tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient, or (as others expreſs it) <hi>aerial</hi> figure of the Croſs, which comes not within the wideſt notion of an <hi>Image;</hi> or if it were ſo, is ſo very tranſient, that it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides not ſo long as to be capable of becoming any <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject or medium of Worſhip,</hi> any further than any words we uſe in Worſhip may do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The uſe even of this tranſient ſign, bears no kind of Conformity or likeneſs with the uſe of it in the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> They uſe it upon numberleſs occaſions beſide Baptiſm. If they enter in, or go out of Church, or a Friends Houſe; when they ſay their Prayers, or are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at any Religious Solemnity. If ſtartled at Thunder, taken in a ſtorm, frighted with a ſpectrum, or are ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41093:9"/>with any kind of Fear or Aſtoniſhment, they bleſs themſelves ſtill, and take refuge under this ſign of the Croſs, which they will make upon themſelves. If they viſit the ſick, adminiſter the extreme Unction, or indeed perform any of their other <hi>Sacraments</hi> (ſo call'd by them,) the tranſient ſign of the Croſs muſt begin and cloſe all. But then, in the Sacrament of Baptiſm, the uſe of <hi>this ſign is</hi> ſo exceedingly different, as well in the nauſeous Repetitions of it before and afterward, in the Forehead, in the Mouth, and upon the Breſt: as alſo, the Monſtrous Significations according to the divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whereon it is impreſt, that nothing can be more. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that it is not us'd at the <hi>time,</hi> nor with the <hi>form of words</hi> that we uſe it with. So that, there is not the leaſt agreement betwixt us and them, either in the uſe, or in the ſignificancy of this Ceremony; and ſo no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable offence can be taken at it, upon any Symboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of <hi>ours</hi> with the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> in it. All this might be further confirm'd by giving a particular view of the <hi>Roman Ritual,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Caſe about the Ch. of Engl. Symbol. with the Ch. of Rome, p.</hi> 10.11.12.</note> as to what reſpects their office for Baptiſm; but this is done by a better hand upon another <hi>Caſe</hi> of this kind.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Although it cannot be deny'd but the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> hath greatly abus'd this Ceremony to very ill purpoſes of Superſtition, yet doth not this make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to continue the reform'd uſe of it amongſt us, that have profeſſedly ſeparated from the Corruptions of <hi>that Church.</hi> It is a Principle that ſome of our <hi>Brethren</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine they are very well fortify'd in, from ſome inſtances in the <hi>Gld Teſtament,</hi> viz. that whatever hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd to Idolatrous or Superſtitious purpoſes, ſhould <hi>eo nomine</hi> be aboliſht. But perhaps they would find this much more a queſtion than they have hitherto preſum'd, if they would conſider, that if this Principle were true,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41093:10"/>it would go nigh to throw a ſcorn upon all or moſt ſo the Reformations that have been made from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> for they do not ſeem to have govern'd themſelves by this Rule. Some of them in their publick Confeſſions declaring, that they might lawfully retain ſuch Rites or Ceremonies as are of advantage to Faith, the Worſhip of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confeſſ. Bohem. Art.</hi> 15.</note> or Peace and Order in the Church, <hi>though they had been introduc'd by any Synod, or Biſhop, or Pope, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a Principle that would render Chriſtianity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable, becauſe no Circumſtance, no Inſtrument, no Miniſtry in Worſhip, but may have been ſome way or other abus'd and deſecrated by <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Romiſh</hi> Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. It would make every Garment of what ſhape, or of what colour ſoever, unfit for uſe in our Religious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices: for, not only the White, but the Red, the Green, and the Black, have been us'd (even for the ſignifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their reſpective colours) by the <hi>Gentile,</hi> or the <hi>Romaniſt</hi> to very ſuperſtitious purpoſes in divine Worſhip. It would condemn the Practice of thoſe very Perſons that would pretend this to be their Principle. For they have ſew of them carry'd it to that height as to aboliſh <hi>Churches, Fonts,</hi> or other <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils,</hi> but have thought fit to make uſe of them in the ſame ſervices of Religion as formerly, though not in thoſe modes by which they were abus'd to Superſtition and Idolatry. All which they ſhould not do, if either the Principle had any real Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in it ſelf, or they acted in any due conſiſtency with the Principle they pretend.</p>
            <p>That which our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren</hi> urge, (as they think) of the greateſt force and pertinency in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is the example of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> who when he found <hi>the brazen Serpent,</hi> which God himſelf had directed to be ſet up for the Healing of thoſe that had been ſtung with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41093:10"/>
               <hi>Fiery Serpents,</hi> abus'd to downright Idolatry: He would not endeavour to recover it to the firſt deſign of its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that is, to keep it ſtanding only as a memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of Gods Power and goodneſs, who had done ſuch great and beneficial things amongſt them by it: but without any more ado, takes it away from all further view of the People, breaks it in pieces, and calls it <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huſhtan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> xvi. 1.4.</note> i. e. let's the People ſee it was <hi>a thing of Braſs</hi> and nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, Firſt, Although it is very natural to mankind to govern themſelves more by example than precept, yet, Arguments fetcht from examples, generally are not the trueſt way of reaſoning; and that partly upon this very account, namely, the proneneſs we have toward example, and Byaſs and Prejudice we may the eaſilier be drawn away with, upon that account. But chiefly, becauſe in alledging examples, it is very rare that we can hit the Caſe perfectly right. It may be ſaid of <hi>Examples,</hi> as it is of <hi>Similitudes;</hi> they ſeldom do <hi>Currere quatuor pedibus,</hi> they do not perfectly reach the thing intended to be prov'd, but are ſo widely different, or defective in ſome one or other Circumſtance, that there is not that parity of Reaſon that ought to be; and the varying of Circumſtances may much alter the Caſe. Which very thing apparently falls out in this very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For certainly, if the example be concern'd in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing with reſpect to our practice, it may ſeem to prove nothing further than the neceſſity of taking away (not what hath been us'd only to Idolatrous purpoſes, but) what it ſelf hath been, and at that inſtant is, a meer Idol. This was the Circumſtance of the <hi>brazen Serpent,</hi> it was by Cuſtom become a real Idol; it had been ſo for a long time, was ſo at that inſtant, when <hi>Hezekiah</hi> brake it to pieces: <hi>to thoſe days the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>did
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41093:11"/>burn Incenſe unto it.</hi> So that, thus far perhaps this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance might affect us, that, were there any <hi>Crucifix,</hi> or material image of our Saviour upon the Croſs, now ſtanding, to which People for ſome Ages had given, and for the generality did ſtill give divine honour; it would then indeed concern the Government, in their Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Idolatries of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> to take away and aboliſh <hi>this</hi> and all other <hi>Images</hi> of this kind. This perhaps anſwers the pattern pretty much, and copieth out <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s wiſe and good Action; and this accordingly is entirely done in <hi>our Church;</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſuch <hi>Image</hi> abiding now amongſt us, to which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny adoration is publickly avow'd, or that can be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have ſuch ſnare in it, as to hazard any general Idolatry. What proportion doth our <hi>Aerial ſign of the Croſs</hi> (toward which there is no intention, nor indeed any poſſibility of giving any divine Worſhip,) what proportion doth this bear to the material figure of the <hi>brazen Serpent,</hi> to which they had for a long time actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>burnt Incenſe,</hi> did it <hi>to thoſe very days,</hi> and gave ſuch Evidence of their Inveteracy in Idolatry, that there ſeem'd no moral likelihood of preventing it by any other courſe than breaking the <hi>Idol</hi> to pieces, and letting them ſee what a meer <hi>lump of Braſs</hi> they had been Worſhipping? But then,</p>
            <p n="2">2. If Example were a good way of Arguing, we find by <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s practice in other things, he did not think it an indiſpenſible Duty in him to aboliſh every thing that had been made uſe of to Idolatry, if they did not prove an immediate ſnare at that time; for, as to Temples which <hi>Solomon</hi> had erected for no other end but the Worſhip of falſe Gods in them, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.7. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did not make it his buſineſs to deſtroy them, as being in his time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn and neglected things, of which no bad uſe was then
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41093:11"/>made. Although indeed King <hi>Joſiah</hi> afterward (proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly upon the encreaſe of Idolatry, and renewed uſe of thoſe places) foued it expedient to lay them wholly waſte. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.13.</p>
            <p>And thus much I have thought fit to ſay as to that firſt Head of Objection againſt the ſign of the Croſs, as it is cry'd out againſt as <hi>a Relick of Popery,</hi> and had been ſo deprav'd by the Superſtitious uſe of it in the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> I cannot but acknowledg this to be the weakeſt part of their plea againſt it; and probably <hi>our Brethren</hi> know it to be ſo too: yet, becauſe it is moſt affecting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt common People, and ſeems to have made the deepeſt impreſſion upon thoſe that are not ſo well fitted for profound and ſolid reaſoning, I have choſen to be the larger here, that even the meaneſt capacities may ſee that the Sign of the Croſs, as we uſe it, was not intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd by the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> but was of a much ancien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter date: That the uſe we make of it bears no Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity at all with <hi>that Church</hi> in their uſing it: that by our different uſage we keep at a ſufficient diſtance; nay, perhaps are in leſs likelyhood of falling into the Snare of their Communion, than if it had been utterly aboliſht: In a word, that that very Principle, upon which the charge of <hi>Popery</hi> is laid as an Argument againſt the Croſs, is it ſelf weak and fallible; nor are we bound by any Precept or Example in Holy Writ, to throw off the uſe of any one thing meerly becauſe the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> hath abus'd it. It hath prov'd a mighty inconvenience to the Church, that People have been thrown into ſo precipitant a Zeal of removing themſelves to the utmoſt extreams from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> that they have been almoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to determine in any action or circumſtance of Divine Worſhip, leſt it ſhould ſome way or other, have been Prophan'd and made unwarrantable by their practice.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41093:12"/>This is that gave riſe to the miſchievous Enthuſaſms in <hi>Germany,</hi> that ended in ſuch bloody and barbarous Pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, as well as ſenſleſs and ridiculous Principles taken up and maintain'd by the Anabaptiſts there. I am loth to mention the horrid confuſions of our own Age and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which yet perhaps we were wrought up into by this very humour; I mean, a reſtleſs fondneſs for ſome additional refinements ſtill, which our <hi>Church</hi> had not thought fit to make.</p>
            <p>I cannot but inwardly reverence the Judgment, as well as love the Temper, of our firſt Reformers, who in their firſt Separations from <hi>Rome,</hi> were not nice or ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous beyond the juſt reaſons of things. Doubtleſs they were in earneſt enough, as to all true Zeal againſt the Corruptions of <hi>that Church,</hi> when they ſeal'd the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded offence they took at them, with their warmeſt bloud; and cheerfully underwent all the hardſhips that Primitive Chriſtians ſignalized their Profeſſion with, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than they would intermix with <hi>Rome,</hi> in any uſage of Worſhip, or Article of Faith that had the leaſt ſavour of Idolatry, Superſtition, or falſe Religion at all in it. And yet theſe Holy and Wiſe Men, when they had the Power and Opportunity of Reforming, wholly in their Hands, being equally jealous of <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> as they were of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> would not give themſelves up to thoſe <hi>fantaſtick Antipathies</hi> as to aboliſh this or that Ceremony, meerly becauſe it had been in uſe amongſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> if ſome other very ſubſtantial Reaſon did not put in its claim againſt it. And verily, had they not Governed themſelves in theſe temperate and unbyaſt methods of Reformation, they would not ſo eaſily have ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified themſelves to their Adverſaries, or the World; or have made it ſo evident (as by their wiſe management they did) that what was done by them was from the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41093:12"/>mere urgencies of Conſcience and Reaſon, and not the wantonneſs of Change and Innovation. So that, where any mean honeſtly (as I doubt not but many of thoſe do, that Diſſent from us in this particular circumſtance of the Croſs in Baptiſm) they ought to have their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon very well awake, that the meer charge of <hi>Popery</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any diſputed point, may not ſo prejudice them in their enquiries into things as to leave no Room for debate and mature Conſideration.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The other head of Objection againſt the ſign of the Croſs in Baptiſm is, <hi>that it ſeems the introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of a new Sacrament, which having not the warranty of our Lord and Maſter Chriſt Jeſus, muſt needs be a very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive invaſion of his Rights, whoſe Royal Prerogative alone it is, to inſtitute what Sacraments he pleaſeth in his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Objection ſeems to point at a twofold argument. The one, with reſpect in Common to all thoſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in Worſhip, which for <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> are appointed by the Governours of the Church, but not antecedently preſcrib'd and enjoyn'd in the word of God. For, to do this, our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren</hi> have generally affirm'd it a bold and unwarrantable intruſion upon our <hi>Lord and Maſter,</hi> who was <hi>faithful to him that appointed him, as alſo</hi> Moſes <hi>was faithful in all his Houſe,</hi> that is, in preſcribing to the <hi>Jews</hi> all their modes and uſages in Worſhip, from which they were not to vary or deviate, to add or diminiſh in any one Circumſtance.</p>
            <p>This I ſhall take no further notice of, than as it may neceſſarily intermix it ſelf with the queſtion particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in hand about the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm,</hi> partly becauſe I would keep as ſtrictly as may be to this diſtinct <hi>Caſe,</hi> and eſpecially, becauſe this Caſe [of doing nothing in or about the Worſhip of God, but what is expreſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41093:13"/>and appointed by <hi>him</hi> in his word] hath been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother's province; ſo that, I ſhall only ſay, the Cuſtoms of the Jewiſh Church it ſelf, (which <hi>our Brethren</hi> would make their main inſtance in this matter,) do make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt it. They did unqueſtionably take up ſome uſages wherein <hi>Moſes</hi> had given no antecedent directions, which yet it is evident were not unlawful upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, becauſe our <hi>Bleſſed Lord</hi> did not only not blame or accuſe them of Encroachment or Superſtition, but <hi>himſelf</hi> practis'd &amp; comply'd with them; this, amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things, hath been clear'd up in the inſtance of their Synagogue Worſhip, and upon another occaſion may be further inſiſted on by and by. Beſides, it is plain, this was no Rule amongſt the primitive Chriſtians in the firſt ages of the Goſpel, not to add, the inexpediency and unfitneſs of this Rule to the very Oeconomy and Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Chriſtianity, which was to diffuſe it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all Nations, and all kinds of People, who did ſo infinitely differ from one another, both in their Cuſtoms, and in the Significations of thoſe Cuſtoms too, that it muſt have been a vaſt and bulky <hi>digeſt</hi> of Laws indeed, that muſt have ſuited all Countries, were every Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Punctilio in divine Worſhip to have been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedently preſcrib'd. All this hath been with ſo much clearneſs made out by ſeveral Hands, that I am apt to think at this time of the day, <hi>our Brethren</hi> do not expect or ſtand in need of further Conviction in this point, and ſeem in ſome meaſure agreed that this Poſition of theirs will not hold water.</p>
            <p>It is the other part of the Objection therefore, that will fall more directly under our conſideration at this preſent; and that is, that our uſing the <hi>ſign of the Croſs</hi> in Baptiſm, doth ſeem to run into the nature of a <hi>new Sacrament.</hi> And this is that they mean, when they tell
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41093:13"/>
               <hi>Sacrament.</hi> And this is that they mean, when they tell us, <hi>it is an outward Viſible ſign of an inward inviſible Grace, whereby a Perſon is dedicated to the Profeſſion of, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Redeemer.</hi> That it is <hi>a dedicating means to conſecrate us to God;</hi> that it <hi>ſignifies our covenanting engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and is as a Badg and Symbol of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> that it <hi>repreſents Chriſt dying on the Croſs, and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies our being liſted under Chriſt;</hi> that it is <hi>an addition to Baptiſm;</hi> that it <hi>adds another Sacrament to Baptiſm: And that it is uſed as an engaging Sign, in our firſt and ſolemn covenanting with Chriſt, and the duties whereunto we are really oblig'd by Baptiſm, are more expreſly affixt to that aery Sign than to the Holy Sacrament.</hi> With many other Expreſſions of this kind, which we may find interſpers'd in the ſeveral writings of the Nonconformiſts, where they take occaſion to diſpute this Ceremony. This of the Croſſes <hi>having at leaſt the ſemblance of a Sacrament,</hi> is indeed the only Objection the <hi>Presbyterian Brethren</hi> inſiſt upon in their <hi>exceptions againſt ſome paſſages in the preſent Liturgy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to this therefore, firſt, I muſt needs ſay, I have ſometimes wonder'd that the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> it ſelf, hath been ſo well agreed upon amongſt us. The <hi>Fathers</hi> have us'd it ſo much at large in their writings that it would ſometimes be difficult to underſtand what they mean by it: and <hi>our Brethren,</hi> upon the ſame reaſons by which ſeveral other exceptions have been made, might have diſallow'd and rejected it as a <hi>word</hi> by no means <hi>Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> but <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Heatheniſh.</hi> However, ſince by a long reception of the <hi>word</hi> into the Church, it ſeems a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on all ſides, what the Senſe and Acceptation of it ſhould be; my buſineſs will be to ſhew, 1. What we are agreed in as to the Notion of a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> and then 2. to make it plain, that as <hi>our Church</hi> never did deſign or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41093:14"/>intend, by the uſe of the <hi>Croſs</hi> in Baptiſm to make any <hi>new Sacrament</hi> of it; ſo, in the nature of the thing, it hath not any <hi>ſemblance of a Sacrament,</hi> according to the Notion of a <hi>Sacrament</hi> that both ſides are agreed in.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As to our being agreed in the Notion of a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> I muſt preſume <hi>our Church</hi> in her publick ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, hath given that definition of it, which no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church, but approves and allows of. That is, that <hi>it is an outward and Viſible Sign of an inward and Spiritual Grace given to us, Ordain'd by Chriſt himſelf, as a means whereby we receive the ſame, and a Pledg to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us thereof.</hi> It is true, the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> in their larger Catechiſm do in that queſtion of their's [<hi>what is a Sacrament?</hi>] put in an expreſſion or two, that point at ſome Opinions, wherein they may be no more agreed amongſt themſelves, than they are with ſome of our Church. But then, in their next queſtion [<hi>what are the parts of a Sacrament</hi>] they give us the ſame account with that of our Church-Catechiſm, only a little vary'd in the words, <hi>viz. The parts of a Sacrament are two, the one, an outward ſenſible ſign uſed according to Chriſts own appointment: the other, an inward and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Grace thereby ſignifi'd.</hi> by all which it is evident, we are well enough agreed in the Common acceptation of the word <hi>Sacrament.</hi> And therefore,</p>
            <p>Secondly, I proceed to ſhew, that as our Church never did deſign or intend, by the uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm, to make any <hi>new Sacrament</hi> of it, ſo according to the common Notion wherein we are agreed as to the word <hi>Sacrament,</hi> there is not <hi>any ſemblance of a Sacrament</hi> it can juſtly be charg'd with.</p>
            <p>And here I might, not without ſome reaſon, inſiſt, that as we are agreed in the Definition of a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> that both the <hi>outward Sign</hi> muſt ſignifie an <hi>inward Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41093:14"/>Grace,</hi> and alſo muſt have its <hi>expreſs inſtitution</hi> and <hi>appointment from Chriſt,</hi> we, that never ſuppos'd the uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm could confer Grace, nor have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made the leaſt pretext to any Divine appointment for it, ought not to be charg'd as introducing a <hi>new Sacrament,</hi> when it hath no pretenſions to any one thing that is of the Eſſence of a Sacrament. But I am willing to follow the Argument as they have laid it. They ſay therefore, that however, we do not call or account it an <hi>Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> yet foraſmuch as we bring a Ceremony into the Church, which in the Significations of it ſeems <hi>tanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount</hi> to a Chriſtian Sacrament, we do thereby uſurp the Prerogative of our great Lord and Maſter, <hi>ſetting up our Poſts againſt his Poſt, and our Threſhold again his Threſhold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This they ſay we do partly, 1. as we make the Croſs a ſign betokening our Faith, and Chriſtian courage, when in applying it to the Baptis'd Perſon, we ſay we do it <hi>in token that hereafter he ſhall not be aſham'd to confeſs the Faith of Chriſt Crucifi'd,</hi> &amp;c. And partly 2. when by an intire Repreſentative of <hi>our Church</hi> it is determin'd, that by the ſign of the Croſs, the Baptis'd Perſon is <hi>dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the ſervice of him that dy'd upon the Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, they ſay that by making the ſign of the Croſs <hi>in token that hereafter,</hi> &amp;c. we apply ſuch Significations to it, that run it into the nature of a Sacrament, uſing it as <hi>an outward Viſible ſign of an Inward Spiritual Grace.</hi> As to this, we muſt ingeniouſly confeſs, that we make uſe of no Rite or Ceremony in <hi>our Church,</hi> but it is with this deſign, that it ſhould be Significant of ſome thing or other. It would be an odd piece of pageantry indeed, to uſe this or that geſture or action in our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſervices, that ſhould have no Signification at all in it, and to account it therefore <hi>Innocent,</hi> becauſe it were <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41093:15"/>It is the Significancy of it, that makes it uſeful or proper, and if there were nothing of that in it, it would be very diſallowable. But then, though our Ceremonies are ſignificant, and any of them us'd as Memorative Signs to put us in mind of any <hi>Duty</hi> or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation toward God, they are not therefore <hi>an outward Viſible ſign of an inward Spiritual Grace;</hi> that is, they are not in the nature of any ſeal or aſſurance from God of <hi>his Grace</hi> to us, but hints and remembrances of ſome Obligation <hi>we</hi> are under with reſpect to God. And that this kind of ſignificant uſages have been all along arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily taken up, without any Imputation of <hi>introducing a new Sacrament,</hi> may be made out, both from the practice of the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> notwithſtanding the punctual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions deliver'd to them by <hi>Moſes.</hi> From the practice of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> and that, both in the very firſt ages of it, and alſo in all the later Reformations that have been made.</p>
            <p>Firſt, take we a view of the <hi>Jewiſh Church;</hi> and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may obſerve that in their very <hi>Paſſover,</hi> about which, both thing and Circumſtances, they had ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs directions by <hi>Moſes</hi> before they went out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> yet did they in ſome ages following conſiderably vary, not only in their time of keeping it, which having been originally appointed on the <hi>Tenth,</hi> they chang'd it to the <hi>Fourteenth</hi> day of the Month: but in the geſture too. In the firſt inſtitution of it, they were <hi>to eat it with their loins girded, their ſhooes on their feet, and ſtaff in their hand,</hi> and all as a token of the haſte they were then in. This geſture of eating the Paſſover, it is not ſo certain how long it continu'd in the <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> after their coming out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as it is unqueſtionable it was chang'd into a <hi>diſcumbing</hi> poſture (that is, a poſture
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41093:15"/>wherein they took their ordinary meals) long before the days of our Saviour, and that ſo warrantably too, that our Saviour himſelf uſed it. And yet, this very po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture they had taken up (if we will believe an Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor that was no great friend to the Ceremonies of <hi>our Church</hi>) had its Signification too;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V. Ainſw. in Exod.</hi> 12.3.</note> for he tells us that they did it <hi>in ſign of their reſt and ſecurity otherwiſe than they had in</hi> Egypt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another inſtance in the <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> might be that of the <hi>Altar of Witneſs,</hi> which <hi>Phineas,</hi> after he had made a jealous enquiry upon, approv'd of,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as a ſtanding me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial that they on the other ſide <hi>Jordan</hi> profeſt the true God, had Relation to the other tribes, and a Right to the Service of God in the <hi>Tabernacle of the Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But that which ſeems to come neareſt us is what the Jewiſh Authors do frequently take notice of, and that is, that as to thoſe whoſe Office entitled them to <hi>the Anointing</hi> (which by all that doth very evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, were only <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi>) although the <hi>Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Oyl,</hi> as to its confection and ingredients, and the manner of doing it (as one would think) were parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly enough preſcrib'd by God; yet did the Jews a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves bring in the uſe of a Significative ſign in doing it, which ſeems no where diſallow'd, or charg'd as an invaſion of Gods Holy Inſtitutions: this was, to Anoint the Heads of their <hi>Kings</hi> with the figure of a <hi>Crown,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maimon. H. Melachim.</hi>
               </note> and their <hi>Prieſts</hi> with the figure of an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> כ or the <hi>Greek</hi> χ. Not to add, that the <hi>Synagogue Worſhip,</hi> the <hi>Rites of Marriage,</hi> the <hi>form of taking Oaths,</hi> and the like, things that had great Significations in them, had not the expreſs Inſtitution of God for their warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and yet were well enough receiv'd in the pureſt times of the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> and comply'd with by our Saviour himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41093:16"/>
            <p>Secondly, take we a view of the Chriſtian Church, and that, both as to the firſt ages of it, and all the later Reformations that have been made. 1. We may obſerve e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from the days of the Apoſtles themſelves, the Church hath taken the Liberty of making uſe of one Rite or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that hath ſignifi'd things of greateſt weight and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to inſtance in a twofold Cuſtom primitively us'd amongſt Chriſtians, that lookt much more <hi>Sacramentally</hi> than our uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm, that is, the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them ſeem'd Apoſtolical, being frequently men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in their Holy writings; and they were immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly annext to the Holy Euchariſt, and in their Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication bore ſome analogy with what that Sacrament it ſelf was in part the token and ſeal of, theſe were the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kiſs,</hi> and the <hi>Agapae</hi> or <hi>Feaſts of Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Holy Kiſs</hi> was perform'd (as the beſt Writers ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally conceive) after all other preparations, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly before they entred upon the Celebration of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr. Caves prim. Chriſt. part</hi> 1 <hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 346. 352.</note> and at the cloſe and upſhot of the whole Solemnity; from whence <hi>Tertullian</hi> gives it the term of <hi>ſignaculum orationis,</hi> the <hi>Seal of Prayer.</hi> This the Apoſtle is ſuppos'd to direct to,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Quae oratio cum divortio ſancti oſculi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegra? Tent. de orat.</hi>
               </note> when he enjoyns the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to <hi>greet one another with an holy kiſs.</hi> And this was kept up with that Reverence in <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s time, that he ſpeaks as if the Service of the Publick Prayers were maim'd and imperfect, if it concluded not with <hi>this kiſs.</hi> This was us'd <hi>in token</hi> of the mutual Communion and Fellowſhip that Chriſtians had with one another, and the unfeigned reconciliation of their Minds, that they came with no inward heart-burnings againſt one another, being that great Chriſtian Grace and Vertue, ſo much inſiſted upon in our Saviour's Goſpel, and after that, by his Apoſtles made one great Evidence of the Profeſſors having <hi>paſs'd from Death to Life.</hi> And yet, that this cuſtom had not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41093:16"/>its Foundation in any <hi>Divine Appointment,</hi> but the volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary uſe the Church made of it, ſeems agreed to on all hands; becauſe afterward, it is not only prohibited by ſome Councils, but by an univerſal conſent in all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, wholly laid aſide, and grown out of all uſe.</p>
            <p>Again, we may obſerve, as to that cuſtom of the <hi>Agapae</hi> or <hi>Feaſts of Charity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20, 21.</note> which in the Apoſtles days probably were celebrated immediately before the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> and in ſome Ages afterward, not till the <hi>Holy Communion</hi> was finiſhed. But, whether they had them before, or after, it is certain they had great Significations in them, not only of Chriſtians mutual Love and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; but alſo, of the equal regards that God and our Bleſſed Lord had, toward all ſorts and conditions of Men; the poor as well as the rich, thoſe of meaner de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and quality, as well as the high and noble, when they were all to eat freely together at one common meal. This the Apoſtle ſeems to point at, in the remarks he makes upon the diſorders in the Church <hi>at Corinth,</hi> that in their Love-Feaſts, <hi>every one taketh before other his own Supper,</hi> and ſo did <hi>deſpiſe the Church of God.</hi> And <hi>thoſe that had Houſes to Eat and Drink in, ſham'd thoſe that had not.</hi> Now, though this cuſtom was hallowed by the practice of the Apoſtles, and had ſo great Significations in it, and was from the firſt, ſo annext to the <hi>Holy Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt</hi> that it always either begun or concluded it, and conſequently lookt much more <hi>Sacramentally,</hi> than our <hi>Sign of the Croſs</hi> in Baptiſm can be ſuppos'd to do; yet is it plain, by the univerſal diſuſe of it, in theſe later ages of the Church, that it ſelf never was eſteem'd any <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might further inſtance in the Ceremony of <hi>inſuffla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de nupt. &amp; concup. lib.</hi> 2.29.</note> or breathing upon the Perſon that was to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis'd, call'd by one of the Fathers <hi>an ancient Tradition,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41093:17"/>which they us'd as a ſign of <hi>expelling the Evil Spirit, and breathing into them the good Spirit;</hi> this ſeem'd to ſignifie more the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> than <hi>Duty of the Chriſtian,</hi> and yet not ſuſpected as any Sacrament. Thus, the Baptized Perſons ſtripping of his Garment in token that <hi>he put off the Old Man which was corrupt according to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Luſts,</hi> doth it not look full as <hi>Sacramentally</hi> as our Croſs in Baptiſm? Yet we find it anciently practis'd without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny jealouſie of <hi>invading the prerogative of Chriſt, in inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting Holy Sacraments.</hi> To ſay no more, what think we of the <hi>trine immerſion</hi> once accounted a pious uſage in the Church, whereby the Perſon being thrice dipt or put under water, at the mention of each Perſon of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> was ſuppos'd to be Baptiz'd in the belief of that great Article.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Advers. Prax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eam.</hi> Again, <hi>in lib de Coron. milit,</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Tertullian</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>Nam nec ſemel, ſed ter ad ſingula nomina, in Perſonas ſingulas tingimur. We are dipped not once but three times, at each name, and ſo are Baptiz'd into the three Perſons.</hi> And beſides this Signification of the <hi>three Perſons</hi> by this threefold im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſion, which <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and not only he, but St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> have mention'd, there are others of the <hi>Fathers</hi> that have ſuppos'd, the Death, the Burial, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our Saviour, together with his being in the Grave three days, was ſignifi'd by this cuſtom. And yet, was this ſo far from being accounted any <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of it ſelf, or a <hi>Sacrament</hi> within <hi>that</hi> of Baptiſm, that the Church hath thought fit to lay <hi>Immerſion</hi> aſide, for the generality; and the <hi>threefold Immerſion</hi> much ſooner, particularly in <hi>Spain,</hi> and that upon a reaſon that made the <hi>ſingle dipping</hi> as ſignificant as the <hi>Trine</hi> had been when it was in uſe, <hi>viz,</hi> to diſtinguiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the <hi>Arrians,</hi> who had taken occaſion from this <hi>threefold dipping</hi> in Baptiſm, to aſſert the three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct ſubſtances, pretending a Teſtimony from the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41093:17"/>Church</hi> by this uſage. Much ſuch a reaſon (by the way) the Reform'd Churches in <hi>Poland</hi> govern'd themſelves by, when in a general Synod they decreed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Poſture of ſitting at the Lords Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>that Cuſtom had been brought in firſt by the Arrians, who, as they irreverently treat Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Synod. Petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cov. An.</hi> 1578.</note> ſo alſo his ſacred appointments.</hi> Which leads to a view of the Church in all its later Reformations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is it not very evident, that in none of our later Reformations, nay even in thoſe of our <hi>Diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> themſelves, but they do in their moſt Religious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities, ſome things that are very Symbolical; Actions that have great ſignifications in them?</p>
            <p n="1">1. There giving to every Baptiz'd Infant a new Name. which both they and we do call the <hi>Chriſtian Name;</hi> this ſeems to betoken <hi>our being made new Creatures,</hi> and <hi>entred into a new State</hi> or Condition of Life, which ſtill they ſeem to aim more expreſly at, in their general care to give the Child ſome <hi>Scripture Name,</hi> or ſome name that ſhould ſignify, ſome excellent vertue or Grace, ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious duty owing to God, or ſome memorable benefit receiv'd from him. Here we have an <hi>outward Viſible ſign,</hi> and this too ſometimes of an <hi>inward Spiritual Grace,</hi> and yet this no more accounted a <hi>new Sacrament,</hi> or a <hi>Sacrament</hi> within <hi>that</hi> of Baptiſm, than we do our <hi>Sign of the Croſs;</hi> and indeed there ſeems juſt as much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the one as for the other, and no more.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe Arguments which ſome of our <hi>Diſſenting Brethren,</hi> have us'd in Plea for the poſture of <hi>ſitting at the Lords Supper,</hi> do ſhew, that beſides what they urge from the poſture wherein our Saviour himſelf celebrated it, they apprehend ſome <hi>Significancy</hi> in the geſture, that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it more accommodate to that ordinance than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for, ſome of them plead for the poſture of <hi>ſitting,</hi> as being moſt properly a <hi>Table-geſture</hi> and doth beſt of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41093:18"/>all expreſs <hi>our fellowſhip with Chriſt, and the honour and priviledg of Communion with him as Co-heirs.</hi> Now in this matter let us conſider; our Lord hath no where expreſly Commanded us to perform this Sacrament in a ſitting poſture; much leſs hath he told us that he ordain'd <hi>this geſture</hi> in token of our <hi>fellowſhip with him;</hi> ſo that, we ſee this <hi>geſture of ſitting</hi> (by the Tenor of their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) made <hi>an outward Viſible ſign of an inward and Spiritual Grace;</hi> and this, not from any antecedent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs inſtitution of Chriſt; which notwithſtanding, this <hi>poſture of ſitting</hi> is not accounted by thoſe that frame the Argument, any <hi>new</hi> or <hi>additional Sacrament</hi> to that of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, Thoſe of the Congregational way have a formal Covenant, which they inſiſt upon, that whoever will be admitted into any of their <hi>Churches,</hi> muſt engage themſelves in; this is of that importance amongſt them, that they call it, the <hi>Conſtitutive Form of a Church,</hi> that which makes <hi>any particular Perſon Member of a Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apol. for Church-coven.</note> Yea, and (as another expreſſes it) that <hi>wherein the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of ſuch a Church doth conſiſt.</hi> We will ſuppoſe then, <hi>this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> adminiſter'd in ſome form or other, and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon admitted by <hi>this Covenant</hi> into an <hi>Independant Church</hi> declaring his conſent by ſome Action or other, ſuch as <hi>holding up his Hand,</hi> or the like. Let me ask them, What muſt they of <hi>that Church</hi> think of this Rite, or Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of holding up the hand? will they not look upon it as <hi>a token</hi> of his conſent to be a Church-Member? Here then is an <hi>outward Viſible ſign,</hi> of What? of no leſs (according to their apprehenſion of things) than a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>new State and Condition of Life;</hi> that is, of being embody'd in Chriſt's Church, engag'd to all the <hi>Duties</hi> and enſtated in all the <hi>priviledges</hi> of it. Will they ſay that this way of admiſſion, either the form of words wherein <hi>their Covenant</hi> is adminiſtred, or the Ceremony
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41093:18"/>of <hi>holding up the</hi> hand, by which this Covenant is taken and aſſented to, was originally ordain'd by Chriſt? or do they themſelves eſteem <hi>this</hi> of the nature of a <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> or did the <hi>Presbyterian-Brethren,</hi> in all their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments againſt this way, charge <hi>them</hi> with introducing a <hi>new Sacrament?</hi> So that, from all inſtances imaginable, both of the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Church, and that, both Primitive, and later Reformations; even from the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular practices of our Diſſenting Brethren, it is very Evident, how unreaſonable a thing it is, that though we ſign the baptiz'd perſon with the <hi>Sign of the Croſs in token, that hereafter he ſhall not be aſhamed to confeſs the Faith Chriſt of Crucifi'd,</hi> &amp;c. We ſhould be accus'd as introducing a <hi>new Sacrament,</hi> or adding the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the Croſs to <hi>that</hi> of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>But then, they tell us ſecondly, we ſeem to own it our ſelves, when in an entire Repreſentative of <hi>our Church</hi> (ſuch as we ſuppoſe a <hi>Convocation</hi> to be) it is actually determin'd, that by the Sign of the Croſs, the Perſon Baptiz'd <hi>is dedicated to the ſervice of him that dy'd upon the Croſs;</hi> and <hi>what can be more immediate</hi> (ſaith one of our Brethren) <hi>than in the preſent dedicating act to uſe the ſign, and expreſs the dedicating Signification?</hi> It is confeſt that the 30th. <hi>Canon</hi> doth ſay the <hi>Croſs is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable badg, whereby the Infant is dedicated,</hi> &amp;c. And the ſtreſs of the Objection in this part of it lieth in the word <hi>dedicated</hi> that is, becauſe the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is it ſelf a Seal of <hi>Admiſſion</hi> into Covenant, and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication</hi> to God, and the Chriſtian Religion; therefore, by uſing a Symbolical Ceremony of humane inſtitution, whereby we profeſs the Perſon Baptiz'd, <hi>dedicated to the ſervice of him that dy'd upon the Croſs,</hi> we have made a <hi>new Sacrament,</hi> and added to <hi>that</hi> of Baptiſm, to <hi>dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> him in our own <hi>invented</hi> way as Chriſt hath in that which he hath <hi>inſtituted.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41093:19"/>
            <p n="1">1. To this I anſwer, that ſurely the word <hi>dedication,</hi> is of a much larger Signification, than that it ſhould be confin'd meerly to the Interpretation, that <hi>our Brethren</hi> would put upon it. The meaning of <hi>dedication</hi> properly is, <hi>the appropriating of any thing or Perſon to any peculiar ſervice,</hi> ſuch as a Church, or Temple for the Worſhip of God: any Perſon to the profeſſion the true Religion, to the Miniſtry, or to any kind of attendance at the Holy Altars. This is the ſtricteſt ſenſe of <hi>dedication;</hi> but then, in a larger ſenſe we may ſuppoſe it apply'd to any ſtrict or conſcientious diſcharge of all the Duties, and anſwering all the ends of the <hi>firſt dedication.</hi> Thus, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Man ordain'd to the Miniſtry, whereby he is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>dedicated</hi> to the work and ſervice of the Goſpel; he may by ſome ſolemn act of his own, <hi>dedicate</hi> himſelf to a zealous and faithful diſcharge of <hi>that Office;</hi> and this, after ſome time that he may have apprehended himſelf <hi>hitherto</hi> not ſo diligent in the truſt that had been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him. This cannot be call'd in any ſenſe a new ordination; but it may with reaſon and <hi>ſenſe</hi> enough be ſtil'd a <hi>dedicating</hi> of a Man's ſelf more particularly to the ſervice of God, in the diſcharge of that Miniſtry he was ordain'd to. And therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In this ſenſe the Convocation ought in all juſtice to be underſtood, when they, in explaining the intention of the Croſs, tell us, <hi>it is an honourable badg whereby the Infant is dedicated to the ſervice of him that dy'd upon the Croſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And yet, I muſt needs ſay, it ſeems hard meaſure upon the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that if thoſe in a <hi>Convocation</hi> ſhould not have apply'd the word <hi>dedication,</hi> to what might be moſt ſtrictly the ſenſe of it, that this ſhould be ſo ſeverely expounded, that no other declarations of their meaning and intention muſt be accepted of, than what meerly the ſtrict and critical ſenſe of <hi>that</hi> word
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41093:19"/>will bear. Surely there are many expreſſions in the <hi>Fathers,</hi> that may ſeem more diſtant from that ſenſe we are willing to take them in; and we ſhould be very loth to yield them up as the Authors or Defenders of ſome dangerous Opinions in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> becauſe ſome phraſes of theirs in the rigour of them, may be preſt to a kind of meaning that may ſeem to favour <hi>them.</hi> There is a neceſſary allowance to be given to ſome ſchemes of Speech, and meaning of words, or elſe we ſhould be in a perpetual wrangle and diſpute about them.</p>
            <p>However, there doth not need even this ſort of Charity for this word <hi>dedicated,</hi> upon which ſuch weight of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath been lay'd. For, as in all Authors it hath been variouſly uſed, ſo is it properly enough apply'd in <hi>this Canon,</hi> for the deſign for which it was uſed; and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration is plain and intelligible enough to the candid and unprejudic'd mind. The word <hi>dedication</hi> (as they uſe it) may properly enough ſignifie a <hi>Confirmation</hi> of our firſt <hi>dedication</hi> to God in Baptiſm, and a declaration of what the Church thinks of the Perſon Baptiz'd, what ſhe doth expect from him, and what Obligations he lieth under by his Baptiſm. And as a <hi>medium</hi> of this declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſign of the Croſs is made, being as expreſſive as ſo many words, what the Infant by his Baptiſm was deſign'd to; the Apoſtle himſelf having comprehended the <hi>whole of Chriſtianity</hi> under that term and denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Croſs.</hi> Now that our Church did deſign this <hi>declarative dedication</hi> (by the uſe of this ſign) and none other, is very evident, in that, though the word <hi>dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> is uſed in the explication of their ſenſe in <hi>that Canon,</hi> yet, do they there refer to the words uſed in the <hi>Book of Common Prayer.</hi> By comparing therefore the <hi>Canon</hi> and the <hi>Office for Baptiſm</hi> together (the <hi>Canon</hi> directing to the <hi>Office,</hi> and the <hi>Rubrick</hi> belonging to the <hi>Office</hi> directing to the Canon) we may obſerve what ſtreſs is to be lai'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41093:20"/>the word <hi>Dedicated</hi> that is, how far they were from deſigning the ſame ſort of <hi>immediate dedication</hi> that is made by Baptiſm, and yet how by <hi>the Croſs,</hi> we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly enough be ſaid to be <hi>dedicated</hi> too.</p>
            <p>As to the Sacrament of Baptiſm, we are all agreed that by <hi>that</hi> we are <hi>dedicated</hi> to the Service of Chriſt, and the Profeſſion of his Goſpel; Now the <hi>Church of England,</hi> both in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> and <hi>Canon</hi> do affirm and own, that the Baptiſm is complete, and the Child made a Member of Chriſt's Church, before the Sign of the Croſs is made uſe of; or if upon occaſion it ſhould not be made uſe of at all. It is expreſly ſaid, <hi>We receive this Child into the Congregation of Chriſt's Flock,</hi> and upon that, <hi>do ſign it with the Croſs.</hi> So that the Child is declar'd <hi>within the Congregation of Chriſt's Flock,</hi> before the Sign of the Croſs be apply'd to it. Beſide, that <hi>in the Office for private Baptiſm,</hi> where the Sign of the Croſs is to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, we are directed <hi>not to doubt, but that the Child ſo Baptiz'd is lawfully and ſufficiently Baptiz'd;</hi> the Canon confirming it, <hi>that the Infant Baptiz'd is, by vertue of Baptiſm, before it be ſign'd with the ſign of the Croſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into the Congregation of Chriſt's Flock, as a perfect Member thereof, and not by any power aſcribed unto the ſign of the Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore, we be <hi>dedicated</hi> in Baptiſm, and the Baptiſm acknowledg'd complete and perfect, before or without the uſe of this Sign, the Church cannot be ſuppos'd ordaining ſo needleſs a repetition as this would be, to <hi>dedicate</hi> in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, &amp; then to <hi>dedicate</hi> by the Croſs again, but that which they expreſs by <hi>dedicated by the Croſs,</hi> muſt be ſomething ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſtinct from that <hi>dedication</hi> which is in Baptiſm; that is, the one is a ſign of <hi>dedication,</hi> the other is the <hi>dedication</hi> it ſelf, as diſtinct the one from the other, as the Sign of Admiſſion is from Admiſſion it ſelf, and a ſignification of a priviledg, is from an Inſtituted means of Grace. It
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41093:20"/>ſeems a thing decent and ſeaſonable enough, that when it hath pleas'd God to receive a perſon into his favour, and given him the Seal of it, that the Church ſhould give him <hi>the right hand of fellowſhip,</hi> ſolemnly declaring and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying he is receiv'd into her Communion, by giving him the Badg of our Common Religion. So that, this is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no other than a Declaration the Church makes of what the Perſon Baptiz'd is admitted to, what engagement he lies under when capable of making a viſible Profeſſion. It expreſſeth what hath been done in Baptiſm, which is indeed not a <hi>ſign of Dedication</hi> but Dedication it ſelf, (as I have already ſaid) as alſo the Croſs is not <hi>dedication</hi> itſelf, but a <hi>ſign</hi> of it. Which Declaration is therefore made in the name of the Church in the plural number, <hi>We Receive this Child into the Congregation of Chriſts Flock, and do ſign him with the ſign of the Croſs,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas, in Baptiſm, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, as the immediate agent of Chriſt, by whom he is Authoriz'd and Commiſſionated, in the ſingular number (as in his Name) pronounceth it, <hi>I Baptize thee in the Name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to what is urg'd above, that <hi>nothing can be more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate, than in the preſent dedicating act, to uſe the ſign, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the dedicating ſignification;</hi> they muſt know, it might have been <hi>more immediate,</hi> either to have plac'd this Sign before Baptiſm, or to have appointed ſome ſuch form of words, in applying it as the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> doth; or if it had been pretended to be of divine Inſtitution, and neceſſary to make the Sacrament of Baptiſm compleat and perfect.</p>
            <p>And thus, I preſume, I have run through the main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate betwixt <hi>us</hi> and our <hi>diſſenting brethren</hi> as to this Caſe. Wherein, I hope, I have neither miſrepreſented their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, nor let paſs any material ſtrength in them, nor in replying to them, uſed any one provoking or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive word. Would they but read and weigh this and the other Diſcourſes of this kind, with the ſame calmneſs of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41093:21"/>temper, and ſtudy of mutual agreement, wherewith (I dare ſay) they have been written; I cannot think there would abide upon their Spirits ſo vehement a deſire for the removal of theſe things; but it might rather iſſue in a peaceable and happy cloſure in the uſe of what hath been made appear was ſo innocently taken up, and might with ſo much advantage, under the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of ſerious and good Men, be ſtill retained. I do not indeed think any of our Church ſo fond of this <hi>Ceremony</hi> particularly, but that, if the laying it aſide might turn to as great Edification in the Church, as the ſerious uſe of it might be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd to, our Governours would eaſily enough condeſcend to ſuch an overture. Inſtances of this have been given in our Age; and our <hi>Presbyterian-Brethren</hi> in their Addreſs to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> do own,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Except. &amp; Pap. of the Presbyt.</hi> p. 31.</note> 
               <hi>that divers Reverend Biſhops, and Doctors, in a Paper in Print, before theſe unhappy Wars began, yielded to the laying aſide of the Croſs, and making many material alterations,</hi> &amp;c. They have not thoſe apprehenſions of <hi>theſe things,</hi> that they are unalterable, and obligatory upon all Chriſtians, as ſuch; or that the laying them aſide, for the bringing about ſome <hi>greater good</hi> would be offenſive to God. I would to God, our Brethren, at leaſt would but meet us thus far, as to throw off thoſe <hi>Superſtitious</hi> prejudices they may have conceiv'd againſt them, and think that as the laying them aſide would not be diſpleaſing to God, ſo the uſe of them cannot be ſo neither. Forgive the expreſſion of <hi>Superſtitious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices.</hi> For I muſt ſuppoſe we put too high a value upon <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent rites,</hi> when we think that either the uſe or rejection of them will recommend us to God, unleſs there be other accidents of obedience or diſobedience to Authority, that will alter the Caſe. Otherwiſe the Imagination we may have of pleaſing or diſpleaſing God in any of theſe things, muſt look like what the <hi>Greeks</hi> expreſs <hi>Superſtition</hi> by,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> I mean, a <hi>cauſeleſs dread of God.</hi> It is a paſſage in <hi>Calvin,</hi> that it is <hi>equally Superſtitious, to condemn things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent as unholy,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> 2 <hi>Praecept.</hi>
                  </note> and to command them as if they were holy.</hi> It is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely a nobler Conqueſt over our ſelves, a proper regaining that <hi>Chriſtian liberty</hi> to which we are redeemed, and would be of far happier conſequence to the Church of God, to poſſeſs our ſelves with ſuch notions of God, and of indifferent things, as to believe we cannot recommend our ſelves to him in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by ſcrupling what he hath interpos'd no Command to make them either Obligatory or Unlawful.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
